<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Abdom Imaging</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Abdominal Imaging</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0942-8925</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1432-0509</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18987909</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2852030</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">9471</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00261-008-9471-x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>New insight of pancreatic imaging: from &#x0201c;unexplored&#x0201d; to &#x0201c;explored&#x0201d;</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>Hiromu</given-names></name><address><email>morihrmu@med.oita-u.ac.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1">Department of Radiology, Faculty of Medicine, Oita University, Hasama-machi, Yufu-City, Oita, 879-5593 Japan </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>6</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>35</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>9</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>10</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2008</copyright-statement></permissions><abstract xml:lang="en"><p>Pancreatic cancer remains one of the most difficult neoplasms for early diagnosis and treatment. Recent advances of imaging including 3D volume data setting in multidetector-row CT (MDCT) and MRI are urging us to focus on the imaging of normal and pathological conditions of pancreatic parenchyme and peripancreatic structures, which are frequently involved by pancreatic cancers and are affecting the prognosis of patients with pancreatic cancers. In this Feature Section, five main topics of pancreatic imaging are addressed: pancreatic arterial territories, imaging of the intra- and peripancreatic venous anatomy and its clinical significance, imaging of the peripancreatic lymphatic network and its clinical significance for staging of pancreatic cancer, perfusion characteristics of pancreatic cancer to differentiate chronic mass-forming pancreatitis, and development of intraductal papillary mucinus neoplasms of the pancreas (IPMNs) to adenocarcinoma and pancreatic invasion. Recognition and understanding of the imaging anatomy of the pancreas might lead to precise staging of pancreatic cancer and to new approaches of less-invasive treatment. Follow-up of patients with IPMNs of the pancreas on imaging seems, at this time, to be the most valuable strategy in the high-risk group selection.</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Pancreatic arterial territories</kwd><kwd>Pancreatic venous anatomy</kwd><kwd>Peripancreatic</kwd><kwd>Lymphatic network</kwd><kwd>Perfusion characteristics of pancreatic cancer</kwd><kwd>Intraductal papillary mucinus neoplasms of the pancreas</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Science+Business Media, LLC 2010</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Pancreatic cancer remains one of the most difficult neoplasms for early diagnosis and treatment. During the past few decades, the incidence of pancreatic carcinomas has increased all over the world, and these tumors have become the 4th or 5th most common cause of death from cancer. Only 10%&#x02013;30% of patients with pancreatic carcinoma have resectable disease at diagnosis. Therefore, long-term survival is extremely rare. Many researchers have been making every effort to find a way for early diagnosis, accurate staging, and effective treatment of pancreatic cancers. However, it was recently reported that use of the brand-new molecular-targeted drug with gemcitebine for systemic chemotherapy of patients with advanced pancreatic cancers could extend median survival by only one month [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. So, when considering the strategy of diagnosis and treatment of pancreatic cancer, the following questions arise: How and what do we know about the anatomy of the pancreas? Do we miss something very basic?</p><p>The term pancreas is derived from Greek and means literally &#x0201c;an organ colored like beef or meat.&#x0201d; The Chinese character representing pancreas in Japanese means &#x0201c;an organ which consists of glands.&#x0201d; On the other hand, the original Chinese character representing pancreas means &#x0201c;an organ of remote region or unexplored territory&#x0201d; (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). It is indeed true that the pancreas is still an unexplored organ, compared to the liver whose arterial, portal venous, hepatic venous, and segmental anatomy had been well established many years ago [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Little attention has been paid to the arterial territory of the pancreas, the anatomy of intra- and peripancreatic veins, and the anatomy of peripancreatic lymphatic networks.
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Pancreas as unexplored territory. <italic>Upper row</italic>: Japanese Kanji (Chinese character) representing pancreas means &#x0201c;an organ consisting of glands.&#x0201d; <italic>Lower row</italic>: Chinese character representing pancreas means &#x0201c; an organ of remote region&#x0201d; or &#x0201c; an organ of unexplored territory&#x0201d;.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="261_2008_9471_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p>In this Feature Section, five main topics of pancreatic imaging are addressed: pancreatic arterial territories, imaging of the intra- and peripancreatic venous anatomy and its clinical significance, imaging of the peripancreatic lymphatic network and its clinical significance for staging of pancreatic cancer, perfusion characteristics of pancreatic cancer to differentiate chronic mass-forming pancreatitis, and development of IPMNs (Intraductal papillary mucinus neoplasms of the pancreas) to adenocarcinoma and pancreatic invasion. The content is outlined here with some supplements.</p><sec id="Sec1"><title>Imaging anatomy of the pancreas and its clinical significance</title><sec id="Sec2"><title>Arterial territories or segmental anatomy of the pancreas</title><p>It is not surprising that there had been no solid concept of the arterial territories or segments of the pancreas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], because there was little clinical need for pancreatic segmentectomy or segmental resection; also there had been little clinical success of the less-invasive targeted therapy. As shown in this Feature Section, follow-up by imaging of patients with intraductal mucinous neoplasms (IPMNs) of the pancreas may be the most effective way to find the early-stage pancreatic cancer. Pancreatic segmentectomy has precisely been discussed for the IPMNs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Clinical application of the less invasive targeted therapy such as intra-arterial chemotherapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] or gene therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] is in the early stages. In the near future, knowledge of the arterial territories or segmental anatomy of the pancreas will be appreciated for both surgery and locally targeted less-invasive therapy. In this Feature Section, Dr. Okahara and colleagues describe the anatomical variations and arterial territories (segments) of the pancreas using CT during selective arterial injection of contrast medium.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Anatomy of the pancreatic veins</title><p>The assessment of tumor invasion to the portal-superior mesenteric veins is crucial for surgical planning in patients who are potentially resectable. The criteria for evaluation of cancer extension to Portal-SMV were proposed in several previous reports [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Observing the pancreaticoduodenal veins is valuable for obtaining additional information regarding curability, because they have a close relationship with the extrapancreatic nerve plexus and the root of the small bowel mesentery. The anatomy of the peripancreatic veins of the pancreatic head has been well established [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. CT assessments of the small pancreaticoduodenal veins in patients with pancreatic carcinoma can help to reliably identify vascular invasion earlier in the course of invasive carcinoma. Understanding the normal CT anatomy of the peripancreatic and intrapancreatic veins, not only in the pancreatic head but also in the body and tail areas, is a prerequisite for evaluating these veins in patients with pancreatic disease.</p><p>Recently, multiplanar reformation (MPR) in dynamic contrast-enhanced studies facilitated by multidetector-row CT (MDCT) has allowed confident and accurate three-dimensional assessment of small pancreatic veins. Specifically, high-resolution MDCT images obtained using the MPR technique, especially the thin-slice images (1 or 2&#x000a0;mm in thickness) acquired by MDCT and MPR using high iodine concentration contrast media, have allowed the identification of these small pancreatic veins. In this Feature Section, Dr. Hongo and colleagues describe detailed anatomic variation of the venous drainage of intrapancreatic veins by analysis of the venous phase of multidetector-row CT (MDCT).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Extrapancreatic neural plexus and peripancreatic lymphatic networks</title><p>The new UICC TNM classification published in 2002 reflects the influencing prognostic factors of patients with pancreatic cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. In clinical practice, there are very few patients with stage I pancreatic cancer because there is no screening method established (nor risk-group setting) for pancreatic cancer at this point. Furthermore, it is very important to know that even T1 pancreatic cancer can infiltrate surrounding peripancreatic tissue including regional lymph nodes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Despite recent advances of imaging including 3D volume data setting in multidetector-row CT (MDCT) and MRI, little attention has been paid to imaging of normal and pathological conditions of peripancreatic lymphatic networks, peripancreatic neural plexuses, and pancreatic veins, which are frequently involved by pancreatic cancers and affect the prognosis of patients with pancreatic cancers.</p><p>Retroperitoneal infiltration via extrapancreatic nerve plexuses is one of the major causes of postoperative recurrence. The second portion of the pancreatic head nerve plexus is frequently involved and is contiguous to the root of the small bowel mesentery. The normal extrapancreatic nerve plexus can hardly be seen on CT, but it is known that the inferior pancreaticoduodenal artery (IPDA) and vein (IP) pass through the second portion of the pancreatic head nerve plexus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Recently, evaluation by CT is reported to be able to demonstrate tumor invasion to the extrapancreatic nerve plexus showing obliteration of the IP and/or the first jejunal trunk (JT) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>].</p><p>Imaging findings of peripancreatic lymphatic invasion by pancreatic cancer have not been described before, though lymphatic networks exist around the pancreas having close anatomical relationship with neural plexuses and blood vessels. On pathologic examinations, there may be two ways of peripancreatic lymphatic invasion by pancreatic cancer; tumor emboli that fill up the dilated lymphatics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] and tumor extension along the lymphatic channels (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). In this Feature Section, Dr. Sai and colleagues describe the CT features of normal peripancreatic lymphatic networks, and state that areas of increased attenuation in the peripancreatic fat plane corresponding with anatomical networks in the patients with known pancreatic cancer may indicate cancer invasion to lymphatics.
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Lymphatic spread of pancreatic cancer. Axial images of postcontrast CT showed some linear areas of increased attenuation (<italic>arrows</italic>, <bold>b</bold>) in the retroperitoneal fat planes which are contiguous to the cancer of pancreatic tail (<italic>CA</italic>, <bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold>). Resected specimen revealed cancer invasion along the lymphatic channels (<italic>arrows</italic>, <bold>c</bold>) which are contiguous to the cancer of the tail (<italic>CA</italic>, <bold>c</bold>). The foci of cancer cells in the peripancreatic fat are associated with fibrous stroma similar to the primary cancer (<italic>CA</italic>, <bold>c</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="261_2008_9471_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Differentiation of pancreatic cancer from pancreatic fibrosis by perfusion characteristics on CT and MRI</title><p>In some clinical cases, difficulties can arise in the differentiation of autoimmune pancreatitis (AIP) and mass-forming chronic pancreatitis from pancreatic cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Late enhancement of pancreatic carcinomas has been observed on CT by a few investigators [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. On delayed phased MRI, significant differences between enhancement of cancer and benign fibrosis have been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Rich fibrotic stroma in pancreatic adenocarcinoma would play a major role in these perfusion characteristics along with architectures of so-called tumor vessels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>] and vascularity of the cancer. In this Feature Section, Dr. Hata and colleagues describe the time-attenuation curve (TAC) pattern of pancreatic cancer on triple-phase postcontrast CT with correlation to histopathologic features including amount of fibrotic stroma and vascularity. Dr. Yamada and colleagues describe TAC patterns of normal pancreatic parenchyma, chronic pancreatitis, and pancreatic cancer. Chronic pancreatitis and pancreatic adenocarcinoma could be differentiated according to TACs of the second and third phases obtained during triple-phase CT with diagnostic accuracy of around 90%.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>IPMNs as a clue for detecting early-stage pancreatic cancer</title><p>The risk of developing pancreatic cancer for patients with hereditary pancreatitis (HP) is extremely high [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. This poses opportunities for secondary screening in those patients. Otherwise there has been no effective screening method for detecting early-stage pancreatic cancer, though a lot of clinical efforts have been made. Periodic checkups by imaging and/or EUS (endoscopic ultrasound) for patients with main pancreatic duct dilatation or cystic lesions are considered to be an effective method for the early detection of pancreatic cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. The possibility of clinical utility of genomic abnormalities including tumor suppressor genes such as Ki-67, p53, and DPC4 remains unclear. Stool K-ras analysis has been reported as a potential screening method for the early detection of pancreatic adenocarcinoma and precursor lesions such as pancreatic ductal mucinous cell hyperplasia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Identifying the responsible gene abnormalities for early pancreatic cancer using array-based comparative genomic hybridization is just in the early stages.</p><p>Intraductal papillary mucinous neoplasm (IPMN) is a relatively new entity and has been increasingly recognized recently as belonging to a well-characterized group of intraductal mucin-producing neoplasms of the pancreas with malignant potential [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Thin-section dynamic CT has been shown to be a useful modality for follow-up of IPMNs, especially those that have progressed into invasive carcinomas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. When a solid mass in the pancreatic parenchyma surrounding the dilated pancreatic ducts appears on follow-up CT, progression to an invasive carcinoma should be considered and surgical resection is recommended. In this Feature Section, Dr. Yamada and colleagues describe the imaging features of the invasive carcinoma originating from intraductal papillary mucinous neoplasms of the pancreas.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Recognition and understanding of the imaging anatomy of the pancreas, including pancreatic veins, lymphatic pathways, and extrapancreatic neural plexuses, might lead to the accurate staging of pancreatic cancer. Knowledge of arterial territories or segmental anatomy of the pancreas might be useful for locally targeted treatments for pancreatic cancer. Understanding perfusion characteristic of pancreatic cancer, which is determined by the vascularity and presence of fibrotic stroma, can differentiate cancer from benign pancreatic fibrosis. Careful follow-up of IPMNs leads to detection of early-stage pancreatic cancers.</p><p>I sincerely hope that the knowledge communicated in this Feature Section will be shared by many clinical researchers and will underscore the next step in pancreatic imaging and treatment.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Open Access</title><p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and source are credited.</p></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Vervenne W, Bennouna J, Humblet Y, et&#x000a0;al. (2008) A randomized, double-blind, placebo (P) controlled, multicenter phase III trial to evaluate the efficacy and safety of adding bevacizumab (B) to erlotinib (E) and gemcitabine (G) in patients (pts) with metastatic pancreatic cancer. J Clin Oncol 26:(suppl; abstr 4507)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">The Liver (2004) In: Standring S, et&#x000a0;al. (ed) Gray&#x02019;s anatomy: the anatomical basis of clinical practice, 39th ed. Churchill Livingstone, pp 1213&#x02013;1225</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakuhara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kodama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Abo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the vascular supply to regions of the pancreas on CT during arteriography</article-title><source>Abdom Imaging</source><year>2008</year><volume>33</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>563</fpage><lpage>570</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00261-007-9342-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18180986</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seyama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Anatomical segmentectomy of the pancreas head: can this procedure be curatively applied for intraductal papillary mucinous tumors?</article-title><source>Pancreas</source><year>2003</year><volume>27</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>270</fpage><lpage>272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00006676-200310000-00014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14508135</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Anatomical segmentectomy of the head of the pancreas along the embryological fusion plane: a feasible procedure?</article-title><source>Surgery</source><year>2000</year><volume>128</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>822</fpage><lpage>831</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/msy.2000.109611</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11056446</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sasada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Denno</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Intra-arterial infusion chemotherapy with 5-fluorouracil and cisplatin in advanced pancreatic cancer: a feasibility study</article-title><source>Am J Clin Oncol</source><year>2008</year><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/COC.0b013e31807a328c</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18376231</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saraga</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mafficini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghaneh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Costello</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Both HIV- and EIAV-based lentiviral vectors mediate gene delivery to pancreatic cancer cells and human pancreatic primary patient xenografts</article-title><source>Cancer Gene Ther</source><year>2007</year><volume>14</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>781</fpage><lpage>790</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.cgt.7701066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17571071</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ram&#x000ed;rez</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Vickers</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current status of gene therapy for pancreatic cancer</article-title><source>Curr Surg</source><year>2004</year><volume>61</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cursur.2003.07.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14972178</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacKenzie</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular therapy in pancreatic adenocarcinoma</article-title><source>Lancet Oncol</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>541</fpage><lpage>549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(04)01565-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15337483</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loyer</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubrow</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Charnsangavej</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vascular involvement in pancreatic adenocarcinoma: reassessment by thin-section CT</article-title><source>Abdom Imaging</source><year>1996</year><volume>21</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002619900046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8661549</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyake</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Aikawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dilated posterior superior pancreaticoduodenal vein: recognition with CT and clinical significance in patients with pancreatico-biliary carcinomas</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>1991</year><volume>181</volume><fpage>793</fpage><lpage>800</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1947099</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>McGrath</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name><name><surname>Malone</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The gastrocolic trunk and its tributaries: CT evaluation</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>1992</year><volume>182</volume><fpage>871</fpage><lpage>877</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1535911</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiyosue</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CT assessment of the Inferior peripancreatic veins: Clinical significance</article-title><source>AJR</source><year>2000</year><volume>174</volume><fpage>677</fpage><lpage>684</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10701608</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sobin LH, Wittekind Ch (eds) (2002) TNM: classification of malignant tumours, 6th edn. International Union Against Cancer (UICC), pp 93&#x02013;96</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuroda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Morioka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lymphatic and local spread of T1 and T2 pancreatic cancer. A study of autopsy material</article-title><source>Ann Surg</source><year>1986</year><volume>204</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000658-198607000-00009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3015059</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kayahara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagakawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Konishi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinicopathological study of pancreatic carcinoma with particular reference to the invasion of the extrapancreatic neural plexus</article-title><source>Int J Pancreatol</source><year>1991</year><volume>10</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1748826</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nonami</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaneko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takagi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical significance of carcinoma invasion of the extrapancreatic nerve plexus in pancreatic cancer</article-title><source>Pancreas</source><year>1996</year><volume>12</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>361</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00006676-199605000-00006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8740402</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Extrapancreatic neural plexus invasion by carcinomas of the pancreatic head region: evaluation using thin-section helical CT</article-title><source>Radiat Med</source><year>2007</year><volume>25</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11604-006-0115-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17514364</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Miwa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitagawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pancreas head carcinoma: frequency of invasion to soft tissue adherent to the superior mesenteric artery</article-title><source>Am J Surg Pathol</source><year>2005</year><volume>29</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1056</fpage><lpage>1061</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16006800</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Is there any clinical or radiologic feature as a preoperative marker for differentiating mass-forming pancreatitis from early-stage pancreatic adenocarcinoma?</article-title><source>Hepatogastroenterology</source><year>2007</year><volume>54</volume><issue>79</issue><fpage>2134</fpage><lpage>2140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18251176</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manfredi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Graziani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cicero</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Autoimmune pancreatitis: CT patterns and their changes after steroid treatment</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2008</year><volume>247</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>443</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1148/radiol.2472070598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18430876</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Vedantham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Krasny</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Two-phase helical CT for pancreatic tumors: pancreatic versus hepatic phase enhancement of tumor, pancreas, and vascular structures</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>1996</year><volume>199</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>697</fpage><lpage>701</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8637990</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiersema</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pancreatic malignancy: value of arterial, pancreatic, and hepatic phase imaging with multi-detector row CT</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2003</year><volume>229</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1148/radiol.2291020582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14519871</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Outwater</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pancreatic carcinoma versus chronic pancreatitis: dynamic MR imaging</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>1999</year><volume>212</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10405744</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Choyke</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Imaging of angiogenesis: from microscope to clinic</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2003</year><volume>9</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>713</fpage><lpage>725</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm0603-713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12778170</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Canto</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening and surveillance approaches in familial pancreatic cancer</article-title><source>Gastrointest Endosc Clin N Am</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>535</fpage><lpage>553</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.giec.2008.05.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18674702</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Canto</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strategies for screening for pancreatic adenocarcinoma in high-risk patients</article-title><source>Semin Oncol</source><year>2007</year><volume>34</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>302</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.seminoncol.2007.05.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17674957</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berndt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Haubold</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>K-ras mutations in stools and tissue samples from patients with malignant and nonmalignant pancreatic diseases</article-title><source>Clin Chem</source><year>1998</year><volume>44</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>2103</fpage><lpage>2107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9761241</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biankin</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Kench</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Biankin</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pancreatic intraepithelial neoplasia in association with intraductal papillary mucinous neoplasms of the pancreas: implications for disease progression and recurrence</article-title><source>Am J Surg Pathol</source><year>2004</year><volume>28</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1184</fpage><lpage>1192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.pas.0000131556.22382.3c</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15316318</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intraductal papillary mucinous neoplasms of the pancreas: correlation of helical CT and dynamic MR imaging features with pathologic findings</article-title><source>Abdom Imaging</source><year>2008</year><volume>33</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>474</fpage><lpage>4781</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00261-007-9289-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17680299</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamei</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hongo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Invasive carcinomas derived from intraductal papillary mucinous neoplasms of the pancreas: a long-term follow-up assessment with CT imaging</article-title><source>J Comput Assist Tomogr</source><year>2006</year><volume>30</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>885</fpage><lpage>890</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.rct.0000220801.76276.0f</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17082690</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>